Hi, I'm Dave Jones and this is the AEV
blog number
First up, as usual, is a book review.
Now, I don't actually have a physical
hard copy book this week. The reason
being is that it's available online as a
PDF book for free. Now, what I'm talking
about is
it's called the scientist and engineers
guide to digital signal processing by
Steven Smith.
And it's available at the website
dspguide.com.
And it's available in hard copy form for
those who want it.
Regular hard copy book, about 650 odd
pages or so. But,
Steven's made it available on the
website for free as a PDF download. You
can download the individual chapters
as separate PDF files or you can view
them as HTML. It starts out at the
basics, what DSP is, and goes through
FFTs, discrete Fourier transforms, and
and there's a whole bunch of sections on
digital filtering, so all sorts of how
to implement all sorts of digital
filters, which is which is really handy.
And there's lots of example code, too,
and it's in regular basic.
So, it just means it's
easy to read and easy to translate to
other languages if you need to. And it's
really good.
And the book's easy enough for regular
beginners to read. It's a great
introduction to
DSPs. It's not really highly in-depth if
you really want to know the
ins and outs of DSP, but for basic
applications and how to implement it,
it's it's a really good read. And
further on the book, there's all sorts
of stuff on audio processing
and things like that. So, there's it's
it goes in really in-depth on various
applications of DSPs. So, I highly
recommend it. Check it out.
dspguide.com.
Now, for something that really ticks me
off.
Something I constantly get annoyed with
and I'm constantly finding
silicon bugs.
These are
not software bugs. These are bugs in
actual silicon devices.
Um a recent one I've had experience with
is the PIC, the Microchip PIC 24F
series. I use the 24
FJ64GA
series device in my uh scientific
calculator watch. The list of bugs in
the 24F series uh device I was using is
actually quite extensive and I'm going
to have to actually read a list here. Um
the brownout reset, the real-time clock,
the I²C module, the UART, JTAG, uh SRAM,
they got the size of the SRAM wrong.
It's incredible. Uh
ADC, SPI, and uh a whole bunch of core
functions, voltage regulator stuff, and
and just regular core functions. It's
crazy. The list is longer than my arm.
And they're up to like the fourth
revision of the device or something and
there's still a whole list of bugs in
there. It's just It's just crazy. I
don't know where it comes from.
So, really it's worth uh checking out.
Next time you go to use a new device,
check out the silicon errata first. It
could save you a lot of head scratching,
really.
Yes, I've changed into a
anti-static lab coat. Why?
Because it's myth-busting time. First
myth is
anti-static bags.
You've seen them before, these pink
things?
They're
designed They're supposedly anti-static.
But, would you believe me if I said
they're not?
These are static dissipative.
That means that they will not build up a
static charge.
But, they will not protect your devices
at all, not one little bit, from getting
zapped. If you put your devices inside
one of these pink static dissipative
bags, they're not protected at all. I
can come up and zap straight through
there, and your devices are goneski.
Now, if you actually go to a real
ESD course,
um the the first thing they will
actually do is actually demonstrate this
myth to you. They will actually take an
antistatic bag, and they will put a an
actual receiver inside, and they will or
a sensor inside, and they will zap
straight through the bag, and you'll see
that it does absolutely nothing. And
then they'll do the same thing with a
static shielding bag, and you'll see
that it won't get through at all. And
that's just a common myth, because
people don't really
Well, a lot of people don't really
understand the basics of antistatic and
static control. Now, what you really
need is one of these
static shielding bags, one of these
They're actually a Mylar with a
shielding impregnated
thing inside a Mylar wrap. And these
will actually protect your devices. If
you put your device in there, you cannot
zap through the bag, because they're
static shielding, not static
dissipative, static shielding.
Now, that's why you'll often find
uh
a whole bunch of devices, they will be
wrapped in an antistatic bag for basic
handling on an antistatic bench, and
then they'll go inside a static
shielding bag or a static shielding box.
And the same thing goes for your IC
tubes as well. These are not
typically static
uh shielding. They are antistatic, and
it says so right on the back if you can
read it. It says antistatic, which is
static dissipative. It means the same
thing. Antistatic is static dissipative.
It won't build up a charge. But,
I can zap that chip straight through
that tube, and it's totally destroyed.
So, that's why
um
these tubes must come in a static
shielding bag. And uh for the ultra
paranoid, the static shielding bag will
come inside a static shielded box as
well.
And really,
um unless you're If you want to uh use
ESD If you want to treat ESD seriously,
um
you really shouldn't be
uh
playing with these You shouldn't take
anything out of a static shielding bag
unless you're at a static approved
workstation. Cuz if you do,
you can zap them.
Soon as you take them out of the bag,
right through the tube. Nasty. Now, it's
time for an equipment review. This seems
to be everyone's favorite part of the
blog. People just can't get enough of
gear reviews. So,
all that new stuff from the
manufacturers that uh has been promised,
it's all still in the mail. So, you
know, I'm going to have to uh
just review something on hand again this
week.
Once again, it's of interest to
electronics engineers. This week, I've
chosen the pocket multimeter.
Ta-da!
Now, this one is a Wavetek DM78A.
Uh
I've had it for I don't know, maybe 8 10
years or something like that. It's um
reasonably old. I've got quite a few of
them. Um I use them uh I've got them in
tool boxes at work, in little tool
pouches, things like that. They're great
to put in the car glove box.
Just handy to have in your desk at work.
Just just for when you need it. Now,
there's many of them on the market, but
um
this is this is the one I like and
prefer. It's got the
vinyl wallet, fold over type wallet with
the
fully attached test probes. And that's
what
really makes a good pocket multimeter.
There's nothing worse than losing your
probes. Um so really you need one with
the attached probes. There are others
that have the probes which actually wrap
around the outside and things like that
and they're not really as good. Um I
much prefer these. They fold up in a
little Velcro the probes fold up in a
little Velcro attachment there. And it
just folds over, you can put it in your
pocket, fits in your back pocket real
easy. And they're just really handy.
They range anywhere from 2% to .5%
accurate. So you can get reasonably
accurate ones.
Um
and there's
many more on the market these days.
This is the this is the traditional
model, but there's ones that have
capacitance test and frequency test and
they're really quite handy.
I have never seen a manual ranging one.
They're all auto ranging usually
3200 count or something like that. And
they're just really handy. I think
everyone should really have one of these
pocket multimeters or two or three. And
you can get them quite cheap. You can
get them on eBay and various stores and
things like that. And you get them for
as little as $10 or something like that
these days.
But some of the really good ones you can
pay upwards of you know
80 to $100 or something like that. So
I don't think they're worth that much.
But um, you should have a couple of
these cheap ones around, and they're
just so darn handy, and it's pretty much
all you need for basic everyday use.
Check them out, the pocket multimeter.